(Cara) Hello everyone, and welcome to the latest Smart Company webinar.
Communicating with your staff is the topic today.
My name's Cara Waters, I'm the editor of Smart Company and today I'm joined online
by Ailsa Page who owns A and P Marketing Works, a small business.
So she'll be able to give some insights into how she communicates with her staff.
And we've got Emily Jaksch who is the lady behind HR Gurus.
And she'll also be giving us some information but specifically from the
expert point of view of human resources.
So what you need to do today to participate is, firstly, just sit back
and listen. Audio is going to be automatically
streamed through your computer speakers. And you can also participate through
Twitter. if you @ Smart Company, and use the
hashtag talktostaff. Finally and probably the main way the
most of you will participate is asking questions by the questions panel.
To do that, you just type in your questions in the space at the bottom and
click on Send. I'll then be, putting the questions to.
the presenters from you so on your behalf so, do feel free to fire away its a great
opportunity to have some experts on line here.
And, ask them what you want. Alright and finally don't worry about
hurriedly scribbling things down. Because if you miss something, you will
be sent a copy of the slides and a link to the webinar recording tomorrow
afternoon. And so we'll have all that information
for you. And just before we get going, a big thank
you to our partner for today's webinar, Business Victoria.
as you can see, they're on Twitter and Facebook as well if you want to follow
along. Great.
So, now I'm going to hand over to our presenters, for our webinar,
Communicating with Staff. So, take it away, Emily and Ailsa.
(Emily) Thanks, Cara, Well, today we're talking about, as she
mentioned, communicating with staff. My name's Emily Jaksch.
And I'll be joined by Ailsa Page, who will be giving me some insights
from a small business perspective.
We've got quite a bit to get through. So, as you would know from the content that
we're going to cover today we're looking at how to set up processes so communication doesn't get lost.
Communication around those tricky topics that you probably try to avoid at all costs,
getting key messages across during staff inductions.
The best way to communicate to develop loyalty and build teams; how to let your staff know if they are not
performing and how to praise them when they are.
How to communicate change and the importance of face to face communication. Okay.
So the first topic we're going to talk about is effective communication process, in that it is
really important that you setup both formal and informal communication processes.
The first one is really just having a business plan and making it visible to your staff
So you could have scorecards. I've got clients who had visual
boards on their wall so everybody know exactly what's expected of them on a day
to day basis and where the company is heading.
And next thing is a really simple one, it's around having a job description
and making sure they're kept up to date, and this is around making sure
people know what's expected of them and what their job is. The next one is having an induction and
formal training for your staff also very important and finally having a performance review process.
I guess informally, staff meetings
which lots of people probably don't do enough of
or if they do they are probably not as conducive as they would like them to be
so it's really important to use staff meetings
that have an agenda. Staff announcements via email verbally it's
really important that people are aware of what's going on.
One on one coaching sessions are also really important around communication, people want to know
feedback around their performance. And finally, using social media, you
know, the internal internet, is a great way to publish communication and
make sure that it's not lost. I guess the key purpose of all of this is making sure people understand
what's expected of them, what's happening in the business
and finally what's going to be rewarded.
And I guess I'd like to ask Ailsa what she thinks of all these
different communication processes or what works best
for you in your business.
(Ailsa) Great. Well, look hello everyone.
it's great to be here. Now just to, yeah,
I, look, I think it is important to communicate at different levels with your
staff. Some people are very verbal, obviously.
Other people like to see things written down.
And I think the most important thing is to make sure that whatever's it's in the
job description is actually then, also, that you've got a
consistency of communication as well. But I think it depends on the size of the
business. If you've got lots of people, then you
probably will have a bit more written documentation.
If you've only got, sort of, a couple of staff or maybe some part time staff,
it obviously will be a little bit more on the informal side of things.
But I think it's good to have both, because, if you just have things that are
informal, then, I think a little bit can perhaps sometimes it's not as taken as
seriously as stuff that's written down.
So, one of the things I certainly do with my staff
is I do have things written down,
and then on a regular basis,
I'll check in with them, to see, to let them know what's been happening with the,
with the business, what are some updates, and also just to reiterate again,
particularly for, say, this week, what might be the priorities for this week.
(Emily) Fantastic. That's great advice.
So, I just want to refer to the Business Victoria website.
There's an enormous amount of great content on the site.
So, you don't have to create these things from scratch
I know that is seems a bit scary, but they've got business planning templates,
they've got job description templates, they've got advice on induction and
training. They've also got a performance review
process on there with some advice about creating KPI's in your business.
So please refer back to that. because it will definitely help you if
you are starting from scratch. Okay, so another thing that we wanted to
talk about today is effective induction processes.
So, I cannot stress enough the importance of that first day induction.
Research tells us that the, the key reason that people leave within the first
three months is a lack of induction. There's nothing worse than rocking up on your first
day. And finding that you don't have a desk,
you don't have a computer, and no one wants to spend any time with you.
So making sure that you're ready for that person on that first day is really,
really important. You need to make them feel welcome.
You need to introduce them to everybody. You need to also go through the terms and
conditions of their employment, your policies, and a really good way to do
that is using a staff handbook. There is actually a great template available on
the Business Victoria website if you don't have one which has the basic policies that any small
business would need. Following on from that the first week is also
really important. This is where you really need to provide that on the
job training to ensure that people know exactly what's expected of them and if you don't
have time to do it a really great tip is to use a buddy so allocate that
person an individual. So that you can ensure that you're
controlling exactly what that person needs to know to ensure they can do their
job. Finally, another recommendation to make
sure your induction is really successful is to have follow up
in place for 30, 60 and 90 days. So, that means holding a review with the
person, checking in to see how they're going,
and then finally the most important thing is ensuring that you communicate with
that person whether or not they've completed their induction or not.
Sorry, their probation. A lot of businesses forget to do that.
Whether its in a letter whether you sit them down and say congratulations your position is now permanent,
it's just about keeping those communication lines open in the first 3 months of employment.
So, Ailsa as a small business owner how, important do you think induction is. (Ailsa)Sorry I just jumped in there [LAUGH].
What I was going to say that is that look induction is everything because it really
is the first impression. And as we know first impressions count so
I 100% agree with what you're saying about being organized really, really
important. If you're not,
you know, if you don't at least give the impression of organization on the first
day, sometimes that can unsettle staff. So I think it is, its really worth taking
the time to you know have a fresh desk, have everything ready for them if
they're in the office. You know just, make sure that its all
there. And then I think a big one too is to
really go through all the OH&S, if things go, even if you're in a home based
business you know, that's at home. All of that thing is to show them that
you actually care about them and I think that is really important to get out there
right at the front I mean you know I know many staff have giggled when I show them
the fire extinguisher, I just want them to know that we have it because believe it
or not we did have a fire once in the office. It was a random thing now, but it's really
important that [LAUGH] everyone knows how to use that. So, I think that's a really
a good thing. And if, you know, even if you might be
fairly casual in the way that you are with your staff, you need to be very
professional with your induction. You need to show that this is serious,
that it is work and talk through all those things in a very professional way.
You can still be friendly, but you need to be professional.
(Cara) That's great advice. I've just got a question
there for, the two of you really, interested to get Ailsa and Emily's
opinion. Aah, Kathrine has asked, should the staff
handbook covered the induction include all of the companies polices?
(Emily) Yes I would say that it should. It's a great time to make sure that people
know what the rules are in a workplace and I would also encourage that at the end of that get
them to sign something that they have read and understood all the policies and
that would help protect you later on if there are any issues.
(Ailsa) And I would agree so, yeah great.
I was going to say I would agree if you've got all of that and if you want you're going to be getting lots of staff
particularly if you're not going to be in easy,
you know, if you're not going to be there a lot to supervise staff or just to,
or for staff to ask you questions, then I think the more you can provide to
them, so that they don't feel left out the wilderness is very important.
(Emily) Yeah I would agree. There's nothing worse then someone rocking up on their first day
and then they get shown the desk and then that's it
and they're expected to miraculously know what their job is,
the induction is about, introducing them into your business,
helping them to understand what the rules are for your business and how they're going to I guess be
measured and what, what's expected of them in a performance perspective.
It's really important that it, it's done formally, I would say.
(Cara) Great. Thanks.
(Emily) Okay. So once again I'll refer back to the Business Victoria website.
There's a whole section there about
induction and probation and there's a section page there for a staff handbook for a smaller business to pick up
basically putting your company name and be able to tailor it
a little bit and have a pretty workable document straight away. So I guess the big question is why
do we do this, why do we want small businesses to communicate with staff and that's easy because it is what
drives performance, because its really the way people learn through communicating,
you can tell them what you want them to start, stop, and continue.
And secondly it creates opportunity for professional and personal development
but it's really about providing that coaching to your staff to help them not only
develop their job but help them develop their career. Finally it's about
communicating appreciation, praise and credit for that persons efforts. How else do people know unless you sit
them down and give them a pat on the back.
It doesn't cost anything to give them a pat on the back and say thank you and I know
what it feels like if someone tells me I've done a great job it gives you a massive buck up and you go home feeling
really good about your work and that's what communication is about.
It is really about managing people well, building relationships with them, you're opening that dialogue.
You're improving morale, you're building teamwork and you're setting people up for success.
Then, if you're not doing it, how do your people know what you're thinking, a lot of business owners
probably get bogged down in the day to day and sit in their office.
They don't spend enough time getting out there and talking with their people about
what's going on. Generally the only time that business
owners probably speak to their staff is when they have done something wrong and
they're giving them negative feedback. So once again an essential part of
engaging people on a day to day basis. So, Ailsa,
I just want to get your experience as a business owner of maybe some good and bad
communication feedback type experiences that you've had.
(Ailsa) Mm, okay. Well, I'm going to talk about some good
stuff first. And, and that is,
and it's actually out of, this was not so much when I was in my own
business. But when I was actually managing,
I was actually managing volunteers, and, you know, so this
is people who are working for no money [LAUGH] (Emily) Yeah.
(Ailsa) And one of the things I, I really discovered was the importance of taking
the time out to, when people arrive in the workplace to meet and greet,
say G'day, catch up with them, give them a little bit of time right at the
beginning, but that's been, a, really important
thing to do and that what I found was that then one, because I used to be
worried about all the interruptions that would happen when people constantly
you know, interrupting you. And I always found that,
if you, spent that time initially, and just check in with people then, and tell,
you know, give them clear intructions and things like that then, they're less
likely to come and, come back and actually, you know, interrupt.
So for me that was a really good tip, spend a lot of time first up with
people, but in terms of, you know providing
feedback, look I found that generally, when
you provide some negative feedback [LAUGH] it can be challenging to you, but
one of the good examples was when, clearly,
you know, someone takes on board what you're saying and improves and then
actually, you know, is able to then go on and do,
work even better in, in the role that they had.
So obviously that's a good one. A bad experience perhaps was with one of
the staff that I had, and it was, look, I think the bottom line was I probably
recruited badly, and that was my, my issue there.
So really, the person didn't really have the skills required for the job that we
were, that I was employing them to do. And it was, it did end in tears.
Which I think is every small business owners nightmare.
When, you know, the last thing you want to do is upset someone.
But I think the bottom line was the realization that,
about the lack of matching of the person to the job.
And it was, and it was very upsetting for the person who was employed.
And it was upsetting for me, too. So that was, you know,
that wasn't great. But then you just, you know,
you work through that. You, you accept that for some-,
sometimes, you know, with those hard conversations
they're certainly not easy. I mean, it's like,
It's like a relationship breakdown. You know, they're not easy to have but,
sometimes you need to have them. &gt;&gt; (Emily) Sure.
So, how do you approach that situation with that staff or what did you actually
do? &gt;&gt; (Ailsa) Which one?
The teary one? &gt;&gt; (Emily) Yeah.
&gt;&gt; (Ailsa) Well, I was really honest. I basically just you know, sat them down.
&gt;&gt; (Emily) Mm hm.
&gt;&gt; (Ailsa) I always think a cup of tea is always a great thing to have on hand
&gt;&gt; (Emily) Yep. &gt;&gt; (Ailsa) For both people and you know, and
just spoke very straight and just sort explained that
look, this is sort of the expectations of the job,
this is what I was expecting, this is you know perhaps this is, the performance
isn't really measuring up to the expectations.
I, and then I asked a staff member what they thought and, you know, they
&gt;&gt; (Emily) Yep. &gt;&gt; (Ailsa) They agreed and I guess at that time
that was when the tears came too, and I guess it was perhaps the realization for them
that yeah, it wasn't really working out.
Yeah so then what I did, I was just then turned into a human and not a, a not, you
know, a manager and, and just sort of, you know, allowed the person to be
upset and, you know sort of sat with that really. And then, and then we sort of worked on
some more practical things of what we could do
after that. &gt;&gt; (Emily) Fantastic. And that's a really good point you mentioned that you were honest with them and that is really the key thing with feedback
and communication is that honesty and that a lot of the time honest feedback is quite hard to give and is really hard for that person to hear it
but it's the only way that people are going to learn and grow and contrary to what a lot of people
think, people actually want to hear this stuff, they want to know if they're not performing
and they want to know if they're doing a good job.
&gt;&gt; (Cara) Okay just to interrupt with some questions that we've got coming through
from readers or listeners Lauren has a question for Ailsa, she wants to know is
there ever a good way to deliver bad feedback?
&gt;&gt; (Ailsa) Oooo, good question, look, what do I think?
Is there ever a good way. Look, I think there's a good way, there's
better ways of doing it, you know, and again I think saying,
supporting what Emily said which is that, ulltimately deep down most people just
most people know the truth I actually think anyway so sometimes it can
actually be a relief to just get it out there in the open.
My feeling is you certainly, I don't like that idea of
letting someone know, oh look, we really need to have a talk, and then
leaving this enormous amount of time and stress to develop.
So for me it's about, it's about being kind of pretty clear, pretty up front
making sure it's not about the person, but about the situation.
And, and probably just delivering it sooner rather than later.
(Cara) I think that, that's great.
Sorry just another one from Edwin, who says, I report to somebody who's very
stingy on praise and thanks. &gt;&gt; [LAUGH].
&gt;&gt; How do you in part to your boss that a simple sporadic pat on the back is
better appreciated. (Emily) I think that, they should just tell them
and say that they would like to hear more feedback from them.
And they would like some, you know, more information about how
they're going on a daily basis. I think it's totally acceptable to, to
manage us I guess because we're always doing it. (Ailsa) I mean, I would actually suggest that
during the time that if, with the stingy manager, is when they are giving
you a, at the time they were giving you some praise, I would try, you know, at that point
say, you know, when you do that? That makes me feel great and I just
want to work harder for you or something along those lines.
&gt;&gt; Yes. &gt;&gt; [CROSSTALK] At the time if you could
if you know if, if that could be done at the time so perhaps, perhaps practice
that one keep it you know in your pocket. And when, when you know,
&gt;&gt; suddenly 'stingy' turns generous for a moment [LAUGH] and then you know bring
out that particular comment and maybe then that will, is a nice way of perhaps
letting a business owner know, oh, okay. Because what they really want is they
want their staff to work hard for them and sometimes they don't know how to do
that. &gt;&gt; (Emily) Exactly that's, that's really good
advice Ailsa. I'll agree.
&gt;&gt; (Cara) Yeah, great tip, and we've got another tip, actually, from one of the
people listening in, Greg, and he suggests the sandwich method, which he
said is sometimes the best delivery. You say something they do good, the bad,
and them leave them on a high again. &gt;&gt; (Emily) Oh,
I've actually got a slide coming up in regards to sandwiching
feedback. But I might
talk about that about that in a minute. (Cara) Okay I'll give you one more question then
before we move on. It's a question from Roula who says how
do you deal with a boss who has very bad communciation skills and is constantly
communicating confusing and contradictory messages?
(Emily) Hm, that's a really tough one. I'm sure that everyone's had a manager who has
done this. I've had managers in the past who have done
exactly that and I use to make sure that I regurgitated back to them to make
sure that I was completely clear on what they wanted me to do.
So, if they asked me to do something that was a bit confusing, I'd say, so what you're asking is
this and them get to further clarify. It can be quite frustrating I would
imagine. &gt;&gt; (Ailsa) Can I just make a comment here and
it is interesting I mean that these sort of coming from staff and guess for the
business owners who are listening in, this is really really important because you know
your inability to communicate, affects your staff.
And this is why, I guess, you know, it's fantastic that you are, if you're the
business owners, are listening to this, because this is helping you to
communicate well with staff. And sometimes it's not necessarily
something that comes naturally, and many people in small business haven't had that
experience of managing staff, and so I would actually encourage business owners
to, you know, get some coaching in that area.
Because otherwise the response is, you know, you, what's going to happen is
your staff are going to say, look, you know, I, I'm finding this really hard
because to that particular listener or caller who's out there you know sometimes
I'd say look you had a go at trying to, work with the manager but
sometimes you know it gets too hard and, and that make's you want to go and look
for another job. And I think this is something that small
business owners need to hear. &gt;&gt; (Emily) Yeah I, I agree totally its a really
important point. &gt;&gt; (Cara) Okay, great I'll let you keep going
then. &gt;&gt; (Emily) Okay, so we were talking about the
importance of honest feedback and what we suggest with business owners is that
you provide honest feedback frequently. That you make sure that you're focused
when you're giving it to people that you don't just kind of do it in the hallway,
that you're really specific because, if you're specific with your people about what
they're doing right or wrong, then they'll understand very clearly what you expect
of them. Make sure that if you give them
feedback that is actionable and is in their control.
Make sure that it's balanced, that its not just all negative feedback or all
positive feedback, you need to give both. Make sure that you give it with
attention and make sure that it's timely. So, there's no point saving up 12 months
of feedback and giving it to somebody in their annual performance review.
What you need to do is talk to people about things as they happen.
So, if somebody does something wrong, if somebody is late you need to talk to them
that day, you don't let it go for 2 weeks or save it up until they've been late 6
times. So now I'm going to very quickly go through some tips for
how to give staff positive feedback and praise when they're doing a great job and this doesn't come
naturally to everybody. It is something that needs to be practiced.
And sometimes, managers or business owners might feel quite strange or insincere about giving
people praise or positive feedback. You should practice and do it over and over again to make sure
you get much better at it. [LAUGH] So I've probably said this
before that be prepared, so script what you're going to say.
Ensure that you have an agenda and that you're ready to sit down and give that person
your full focus. I've already just said that.
So be generous, fair and honest in giving positive feedback don't be too over the top but
don't be stingy, it's very important to give credit where it's due.
Be sincere, so if you're not being sincere your staff member will probably think,
what do they want. You know need to make sure that you continue to
give people praise. Um be timely, I've already talked about this,
it's about giving people feedback at the time of something happening not
waiting. This is really important knowing when
to speak privately and when to speak publically. Some people love being praised in public
where as other people find it quite embarrassing and they get really uncomfortable, so it's about
talking to people the way they want to be spoken to.
So re-enforce not only results but also behaviour, so use a balanced approach there.
And it's really important to explain the impact to the team and business, that they
understand the core impact of what they've done and how important it is.
I'm now going to talk about giving negative feedback.
Which is probably the harder one the people probably do quite badly or probably avoid doing.
So once again I cannot stress how
important it is to be prepared. Especially when giving negative feedback, it's probably even more important
that you have an agenda, that you know exactly what you're going to say sometimes it's worth practicing
practicing on another employee. Have really clear specific
examples because the first thing a person is going to ask as well,
can you give me a specific example of when I've done this, and if you can give them
clear specific examples you will obviously have a lot more impact.
And we talked about sandwiching before, but I would say avoid sandwiching
negative feedback in between 2 pieces of positive feedback, because although it might soften the blow, what it
generally does it means that the person recieving the feedback will walk away only
having heard the positive feedback, they won't actually hear that negative
feedback in the middle, and say, Oh well I'm doing a good job.
What is really important too, if you're giving negative feedback, don't try to soften
the blow, be honest, be really constructive.
So consider your language. focus on the behaviour and the issue, not
the person, Ailsa talked about this which is really good advice. And don't make it personal.
Make it very clearly about the behaviour. Treat the person with dignity at
all times. Some people really get off on giving
people negative feedback, you need to make sure that you, you're
doing it with respect and being respectful, so you're not making people feel
stupid the common thing that people do is ask people an entrapment question and
that means asking someone a question they know they don't know the answer to in
order to make them feel stupid. I would really suggest that you move away from
all the ones from using that approach. Stay in control so I would advise people
to, to not do this when you're really emotional or upset, or when the person that you're
giving the feedback to is really emotional or upset, and if that person does become upset and emotional,
you should never leave the room or run away.
You should stay with them and you should try and steer the conversation and continue to explain
what's going on and what's expected of them, what they need to do to improve.
So if the situation needs to be escalated and you feel like you can't deal
with it yourself then I would definitely suggest to get some help and there's lots
of ways you can do that. I'll refer back to the content on the
Business Victoria website. There's some great templates there
and some scripts. that have been developed on some common
you know, feedback situations. A, a really common one is, if someone is,
is continuely late, there's another script there for if you are making
someone redundant. So, they will definitely help you
deal with the situation, but I guess from your perspective Ailsa, have I missed
anything in terms of what we need to continue giving positive and negative
feedback? &gt;&gt; (Ailsa) Well sometimes the only thing I can
say is with, with the way you can also give positive feedback is
through pay raise [LAUGH] and let them know that you're giving them a pay
raise because they've done great job, you know, great work.
Now that is more looking at it perhaps on a longer period of time, some sort of
rewards. I, I actually think you know.
&gt;&gt; (Emily) Yep. &gt;&gt; (Ailsa) Sometimes it's a way,
it's just another way of saying hey, actually we really appreciate you and the
work that you've done. So that might be Christmas presents, it
might be, just things like that because often, you know, staff love that.
And love that when they go oh, wow look what they've given me.
Or little, you know little certificates or something like that which can be
something quite thoughtful. It doesn't have to cost a fortune and it
can mean a lot to people. And the other thing I was just going to
say with the tips for giving negative feedback,
because everyone reacts differently to negative feedback,
and some people are better, better at, handling it,
you know, it can be confronting for people.
Is, I just wanted to say, to allow time. To allow time, not only for the delivery
of the feedback, but also to allow time for people to process it, and react if
they need to. So, you know,
for me, it is about, also making the space conducive.
Not having a space where other people can walk in or whatever else, you know.
And, and when you've put in about, you know, respect the person and, and treat
them with integrity and, and dignity. And I think part of that also can be
just, just be mindful of, of where this is going to be taking place and always
have a box of tissues. (Emily) You know that's great advice.
&gt;&gt; You should always do it, do negative feedback communications in a private
place where it's, people can't see in, because if, if someone does get upset and
they're crying and everyone can see through the window that's obviously very, very awkward for people.
So that's great advice, thanks Ailsa.
&gt;&gt; Alright. So I guess some key tips for tricky
communication situations, even ones that probably some small business owners try to
avoid at all costs. That's when you know, you're maybe
having to reduce staff numbers, you might be making people redundant, there
might be some staff changes or department restructure although, if you're a small business you probably
don't have a whole department, [LAUGH] or if it, it it's performance issues here's some key tips that we think
are really important for these communication situations and once again
it's about being prepared and having a communication plan.
So, for instance if you're making people redundant you need to think about who
you're going to communicate with, at what stages and when.
So, having a plan to do that will alleviate a lot of anxiety around that
situation. So, being prepared for the hard
questions. So it's really good to sometimes sit down
and go, okay, well, what are the really hard questions people are going to ask me
are, and having an answer prepared, and that will make you feel a lot more
comfortable going into those situations. And, once again, be honest.
Honesty is the best policy at all times. And don't tiptoe around people's
concerns. Tell them the truth.
So be open in communicating, involve your people in any decision making.
And this is very important that you involve staff in coming up with
solutions. Most of the time they are closest to the situation
and they'll probably have the best solutions to these problems.
So, they'll also be really much more likely to accept what's going on if they are
involved in the decision making process. So, basically, finally, we'd like
to say be prepared for the fallout, have answers ready to allay fears, don't run
away, stay with your people and they'll respect
you even more and once again, I'll refer back to the Business Victoria website there's some great content
there around dealing with employees. So, here's a recap on everything that
we've been talking about. Communication is a key part of being in
business because people work for people and so, business owners this means you.
So, your people work for you. So, it's really about making sure that
you communicate with your people every day,
about everything, the rule of thumb here is that there's never too much communication in my book,
so people want to know what's going on if you don't talk to them they're going to
find out through the grapevine and if you are the one in control, they there will be a much better outcome.
&gt;&gt; Okay, so communication is directly linked to retention.
And the reason for this is, it's about engaging with your people and involving
them in what's going on everyday, there's no use sitting in your office, and working away,
and not making, not engaging your people to help you take your business forward.
So, communicating with people is obviously going to help them
understand how they fit into the bigger picture.
And so, I guess I'd like to ask all business owners, how much time you
really spend talking to your people and do you think it's enough,
so Ailsa, how much time do you spend talking to people in your business?
(Ailsa) Well I'm going to have to be really honest here and say probably like every
business owner, I could spend more time. But partly that's because,
there is always this conflict between the time that you spend with your staff versus the
time that you spend yourself working on or in your business.
And sometimes there's a conflict, sometimes we think oh, you know, it's,
all this time is getting away from me that I'm spending on my staff and you
feel like it's a waste of time, which is really incorrect.
[LAUGH] So, I guess I just want to acknowledge all those business owners out
there who perhaps feel that as well, which is like ooohh, you know,
I feel it takes up too much of my time to, to manage staff.
Look the bottom line is. It does take up time.
However, you know the time that you actually do invest and spend with your
staff will come back in spades. The whole point of having staff is to
kind of help you get out of your business so that you can work on it rather than in
it. And, you know, you need to invest
for this to happen. And, I've certainly seen business owners
who havent spent the time you know, that can, it means then that
often its quite inefficient, staff haven't got the direction,
and then you end up do sort of wasting a bit of money and energy on that.
So for me it is a bit of a struggle but I make sure that I,
I am organized and spend time to organize what I want the staff to do and
to check in to see how they're going because what I've found is if I don't do
that, it is inefficient. And so even though I feel like I'm
wasting time I'm not, it's actually an investment.
&gt;&gt; (Emily) Yeah, and that's great advice. Talking to staff is investing in your business
and it is quite difficult at times, but it's definitely worth it in the end.
So, the next question, I guess, is, do
you really know your people, and do you take the time to listen?
So, it's not just about one way communication.
It's about, talking to your people. Getting their input, involving them in what's
going on. It's really really important to do that.
And I think Ailsa mentioned that, in the way that you do
communicate with your staff. So, the whole purpose of communication is
to make sure that people understand what is expected of them.
And if you do all of these things and you invest the time you're going to make sure that
your people will stay with you and if they don't they going to get disengaged,
we've heard some stories about managers who don't talk to their staff and impact
that it has on morale. So I'm just going to talk very quickly
about why people stay in a business. And the first reason is around empowerment
and trust and the way that you do that is through communication. The second one is around manager
relationship and loyalty becuase people work for people, so it's really important that as a manager you spend the
time talking to your people. Giving them feedback when they're
doing a great job or when they're not doing a great job and this will help
retention. It's about ensuring that people
understand the bigger picture and this will help engagement levels and ensuring
that people want to contribute to the success of your business and that's what
communication is all about. &gt;&gt; So better results, are underpinned
by feedback and recognition. I think that, we've made that pretty
obvious. So it's really simple.
Please go forth and talk to your people everyday about everything.
So, just before I summarize what we've talked about today, Ailsa, I just wanted
to ask you is there anything that you think we missed or if you have one top tip
that you could give business owners out there about communication,
not only are you a business owner you're also a communications expert working in
marketing, what would it be? (Ailsa) OK, well I think the big one is, is not
to assume that your staff understand what you've communicated.
In other words you need to check in that there is an understanding.
One of the things that has sort of come up,
while we've been talking that I've been thinking about is, many businesses I
speak to, sometimes they, their staff are very passionate and excited and, and very
committed, but they might be putting their energies perhaps into the wrong
areas, and so they're actually going off on a slight tangent to perhaps what
they're meant to be doing. So I think that's probably a big thing, is
really just checking in to make sure that the staff is very clear on what you
expect of them, on what you want them to be doing.
And so then, that needs to be done on a regular basis because if it's not, you
know they can think, you know they can be working, thinking they're doing a great
job but it's in the wrong direction. And, and you know sometimes business
owners don't want to always pull back the reigns but you need to and ultimately the
staff will thank you for, for keeping them on on track
so that you set them up to win as an employee rather than set them up to fail because they are not
doing what they are supposed to be doing. (Emily) That's great advice.
So how do you do that in your business like, do you have monthly staff meetings
or do you do it more informally? &gt;&gt; (Ailsa) Look, I pretty much have a,
my system is that, whenever staff come in,
because I have a lot of part time staff as opposed to full time staff,
I really do a check in.
I actually give them, a bit of an up to date on what's been happening in the
business. Because I'm sure, like many other
business owners, gee, you know,
one week in small business, a lot can happen.
So it's a case of really bringing them up to speed.
And sometimes, you know, we do change direction, because we can.
Because we're flexible, we're small, and we are able to, you know?
You know, adapt to the market. So I, bring them up to speed.
And then, sort of relate how perhaps the changes in the business, might then affect
what they've been doing. And I, you know, reiterate exactly,
well, you know, you were working on this. This is now no longer such a priority so
I'd like you to work on this. Or whatever it happens to be, so I give a
bit of rationale for perhaps a change of direction, and I do that every time
because I've just learned that if I don't sometimes, whilst I think it's all clear,
I think I've, you know, been a perfect communicator and the message hasn't got
across. So I also go through a bit of a, we
almost do a daily, you know, sort of, what are we going to
do today? So that's all very clear and so that
staff, if I'm out and about and not here all the time, they've got something
written down that they're very clear that this is what's to be done.
(Emily) Yeah, that's great advice. Thanks Ailsa.
So I guess, in summary, having the right communication processes and systems
in your business is really really important. And whether they're formal; informal,
you know, all of these tools will help
you, better manage what's going on, making sure people know what's expected
of them, when they're performing and when they're
not. So whether it's a performance review
process, an induction process, your staff manual,
or where it's just a general email announcement.
It's really important to have those processes in place.
I've said this about ten times I think being prepared and having an agenda is
key to successful communication. Be ready for the hard questions and don't
hide and don't shift away from situations where you know there's going to be conflict
or it's going to make people uncomfortable. You, you are the business owner.
You need to step up to these situations and manage them head on, otherwise
it'll just come back to bite you in the end. Practice makes perfect.
So, once again, doing this every day it's going to, you're going to get better and
better at it. It might feel a bit funny to begin with
but if you keep doing it the time it will get easier and easier.
Choose the right type of communication for the situation so whether it be an
announcement or a letter or whatever it needs to be you need to make sure that
your communication's tailored to the outcome.
And finally, face to face, we suggest its always best, how much, how many times have
you sent an email to someone and its either got lost in translation;
things have been taken out of context. It's a lot better to walk over
to the person's desk and tell them face to face or even pick up the phone.
And I think that, that's really about it.
So, basically, go forth and talk to your people.
&gt;&gt; (Cara) Okay, great, thanks so much Ailsa and Emily, we've got a lot of questions and
so, I encourage you to keep on sending them
through and I'll put as many of them as we have time to, to the pair.
So first of all, we've got a bit of an interesting one from Michael.
He said this is the age old show stopper, how to deal with a staff member,
female, who has B.O. [LAUGH] (Emily) Okay.
Yeah, this a tough one and it is a situation that I've had before.
So my advice would be, I would get another female to speak to her.
It might be a little confronting if a male sat her down and gave her some feedback,
but I would sit down and just explain to her about personal hygiene and
the importance of personal hygiene and very gently suggest that, she needs
to wear deodorant. &gt;&gt; (Ailsa) Could I add to that?
&gt;&gt; I would also, in the staff bathrooms, I would actually provide
deodorant and sort of have it there and with just, a little sign, sort of like
you know, something.. (Emily) Sort of um, 'keep fresh.'
&gt;&gt; (Ailsa) Yeah, Keep Fresh.
I like that. There you go.
[LAUGH] Yeah, or something along those lines.
I mean, if you, if humours, well, yeah. It's probably better to keep it straight.
&gt;&gt; Really. (Cara) Okay.
So some sweet smelling tips there. And we've got another question from
Melissa. She says, how do you deal with a staff
member that ignores or disregards negative feedback?
(Emily) Yes, this is common one I guess if someone ignores negative feedback and it's
having an impact on their performance you may need to escalate that to a more
formal performance management process, where you would give them
warnings for failure to improve. So, it may be that you need to sit down
and formally go through things and put in things in writing and let them to know
what the consequences are if they don't improve their behaviour because if there
are no consequences then generally people won't change and they will disregard it.
(Cara) Okay, a bit of a practical issue from Scott.
He wants to know whether there's any tool or software that can help with task
management on an ongoing basis. &gt;&gt; (Emily) Hmm, task management as in, like a
project management tool? &gt;&gt; (Cara) I'm not sure,
Scott, hasn't
&gt;&gt; given any further details. If he wants to send through more but,
perhaps if you can guess for now. (Ailsa) I'm happy to just say look seriously
even just you know Microsoft Outlook if you're on PC, just the, just the
tasks list can be a ripper. You know something like that or if you're on
Google Docs and you actually have a sort of a just even a manual or sort of you know,
who's doing what. I mean that just keeping it really
simple, can be a very good way of, you know, just keeping up, keeping a bit
of a track of it. It's not anything sophisticated but,
it's, it's there and available to most businesses.
&gt;&gt; (Cara) Okay and we've had a tip from a listener, Michael who says TRELLO is a
great free browser task management software.
T.R.E.L.L.O he says.
&gt;&gt;(Emily) Wow. &gt;&gt; Fantastic. There you go.
&gt;&gt; [LAUGH] [LAUGH] (Cara) So we've got
another, question from Kate. She says coming in as a new manager to
introduce and develop new systems, how do you go about introducing those to
existing staff to get them on board and view them as positive not negative?
(Emily) Sure, I guess this is really around change management and the first step in
change management is helping people to understand why you need to change and
I guess the whole thing around, what's in it for me, is a good way to do that.
So involving them from the very beginning in a new project getting their input,
getting them to help come up with solutions will enable them to I guess more easily accept
what's going on is my best advice. &gt;&gt; (Ailsa) And I'll just add to that by also
you know talking with the staff and finding out a little bit about them and
potentially what might be their barriers to the change and being really honest
about that, I think acknowledging you know, because with change,
there's always some you know, negative sides as well as some positive sides.
So I think it's about being you know, open and honest and acknowledging the
negative because sometimes when we're bring in change, we just keep trying
to, you know, promote the benefits of it, but people,
you know, people, in their minds, know the negatives, so by, sometimes by just
getting those out of the way, acknowledging them, then you can, really
can move forward to some of the positive stuff.
&gt;&gt; (Cara) Okay, that's great, Ailsa. Now I've got a question from Melissa.
She says, how do you deal with a staff member that ignores or disregards
negative feedback?
(Emily) Did we already have that question?
&gt;&gt; I think I was going to say we've already answered that question.
&gt;&gt; (Cara) Okay I'm repeating myself okay, that's alright we've got lots more here
to go, we've got a question from Leo he wants to know are teams rewards
appropriate, as well as individuals. (Emily) Yeah, I would definitely encourage team
based rewards, you could come up with an incentive program that rewarded the whole team not
just individuals I think that's a great way to build that sense of team ensure
that people are alligned to the outcome and to your business strategy, so I would
definitely encourage that. &gt;&gt; (Ailsa) Yeah and I would agree as long as
you know, the team is working together, to achieve a goal, because
sometimes, I think it can back fire when there's sort of um, if
certain people working really hard, and then, if then there's a generic reward
across the company, you know, based on a few people's kind of performance, I think
that's when it can backfire. &gt;&gt; (Emily) Yeah, I totally agree, it needs to
ensure that everybody is engaged. And rewarded for whatever the incentive is.
&gt;&gt; (Cara) Okay that's interesting, and Josie wants to know how do you manage staff
that don't directly report to you however you've been asked to manage them by your
direct report regarding projects when a direct manager is not there.
(Emily) Hmm, that's probably a common issue, and that's I guess really around
influencing people. And then, I guess having the skills to, to
try and get people on board with projects when they are not necessarily your employee,
it can be quite difficult. Maybe they could speak to the persons
manager and ask for help. Getting that person to help them with
that project, it's a bit of a tricky one Ailsa, what do you think?
&gt;&gt; (Ailsa) Well the only thing I'm thinking, is that whoever has got the authority needs to endorse the
role that they're putting you into and even though they're sort of saying well
look they don't have to directly report to you I think they're just saying to
re-clarify what they're expecting from both staff members in that situation
rather than just throw it on to someone who's the subordinate and say, sort it out.
You know, I don't think that's, I don't think that's fair.
So I think it's about re-communicating if, if the position has changed so that
there's a different reporting structure or there's a different accountability
structure, whatever. That needs to be communicated by the
person who ultimately has the responsibility.
(Cara) Okay. That's helpful.
And Sharon wants to know how to deal with, it's quite simple from Sharon actually,
but tricky, how do you deal with staff who don't get on?
&gt;&gt; [LAUGH] (Emily) How long is a piece of string? I guess that's a really tough one.
Sometimes you may need to get the staff member into a room and do a bit of a
mediation session to say "Ok, guys, lets talk about the issues here and if you are
upset with each other, what's going on," and try to get them to agree to disagree,
or agree to work together. I found in the past,
sometimes that works but I guess the two people need to be willing
that. If it's about behaviour and people
behaving inappropriately, I guess, are going to deal with that separately.
&gt;&gt; (Ailsa) Yeah look I'd have to agree with what Emily is saying, the only thing I'd
add to it is, it is about identifying, you know, is it just a personality clash
or, or is there some sort of behaviour
that one of the the parties is doing, that is unacceptable.
It's sort of identifying what's going on there. Some team building can always be a
good thing, you know social functions outside the
office can be good, you know.
You might want get someone in that can run some of those, that's often proven to
be very, very effective. But look, at the end of the day I think
it is really important I know that there's, there's 2 sides to it.
One is, you know, having diversity can be fantastic for problem solving and things
like that. But in small business, you know, having a
personality clash, if its a small staff, you know its a nightmare.
So I think sometimes you almost need to perhaps be really upfront to both of them
and say look, this is, you know, this is a bit of a
nightmare and it's putting the business in a bit of
a tricky situation. So have you got some solutions for how we
can work through this? You know?
Yeah, anyway, and I could go harsher but I won't [LAUGH].
&gt;&gt; [LAUGH]. &gt;&gt; (Cara) We've got a tip here from one of
our listeners Michael, and he said, he's actually had an excellent result in a
situation where, the business culture included a large amount of interpersonal
conflict between staff. And what he did was get a professional
trainer to assist with and had excellent results in cultural change and it was
assisted with funding through the enterprise connect and also skills for
growth. &gt;&gt; (AIlsa) Oh, there you go, brilliant.
&gt;&gt; (Cara) Yes, so that's a good tip. I'll give you a final question here.
Martine says she thinks she communicates quite well with her staff and when she
asks for feedback it's always rather positive.
But she still continues to have some recurring issues.
How does she really know if it's the way she communicates or if
the staff are just not listening. &gt;&gt; (Emily) Good question.
&gt;&gt; I guess a tool to get
some, some feedback from her staff maybe a 360 review.
So, she may if she is a small business owner be able to engage a consultant to come out
and do a 360 review process so she can get some balanced feedback, a lot of the time
if it's your manager is quite scary to give them really honest feedback because
you're worried about the implications of giving that feedback.
So to use a 360 review process you can get that feedback in a confidential manner,
where people will feel more comfortable doing that but if that's not an option because
it might be too expensive or it's just not something can be done I would encourage
her to be more direct with her staff and say I want you to give feedback and I'm not going
to get upset when you do so. And give
them permission to tell her the truth. &gt;&gt; (Ailsa) I was just going to say that another
that say we do in, with marketing is when you really want to know what your
customers think of you, is usually what does work, is that you get an independent
person to ring up and and have a confidential discussion.
And then, you know, later on, you may ask the person, is it okay
if this information is fed back without revealing name?
Or is it okay if it's fed back, revealing name?
And often, what can happen is when that is initiated by the business, it's
incredible how people are then is going, oh wow, they really want to
improve this, how they then will perhaps provide honest
feedback and, and then what can happen is it can be delivered to the business owner
in a way that can be heard without the staff actually having to deliver that
themselves. (Cara) Okay.
Yeah, it sounds like there's a few solutions to that one, so good luck Martine.
Alright well that's all the questions we have time for although there will be a
chance if you want to turn to Twitter using the hashtag #talk to staff
to ask a few more questions. But for the webinar section I'd just like
to really thank everyone for participating and thanks for all your
brilliant questions. That's been really insightful.
And, thanks to our partner for today's webinar
Business Victoria. You will have seen a few links up on the
screen during this seminar to the Business Victoria website.
So I'd encourage you to go and have a look at that.
There's a lot of information on there and
when you get your slide pack, you can just click through to those links and
find more information on some of those issues.
So thank you very much, thank you obviously to Ailsa and Emily for sharing
your expertise and to everyone for joining in
on another smart company seminar and, we'll have details of the next one
coming up. Thank you.
&gt;&gt; (Ailsa) Thank you. &gt;&gt; (Emily)Thank you.